Guide to the George Bird Grinnell Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George Bird Grinnell papers
1859-1939
MS 1388
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
16.5
(42 boxes)
The papers, which consist of letterbooks, correspondence, and subject files, including photographs and writings, document George Bird Grinnell's leading role in the American conservation movement. The material focuses on Grinnell's adult life (1886-1938) and details his work as editor of Forest and Stream magazine, authority on American Indians of the West, and active participant in the National Audubon Society, the Boone and Crockett Club, the American Game Protective and Propagation Association, and the National Parks Association.
Grinnell, George Bird, 1849-1938
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the Connecticut Audubon Society, 1984, and Charles Apfelbaum, 1989. Gift of John F. Reiger, 1984 and 1989. Gift of the Connecticut Audubon Society, 1991.
Existence and Location of Copies
Entire collection is also available on microfilm (46,383 frames on 47 reels, 35mm.) from Scholarly Resources, Inc., Wilmington, Delaware. HM 223
Arrangement
Arranged in two series and one addition: I. Letterbooks, 1886-1929. II. Correspondence, Subject files, and other papers, 1859-1939.
Scope and Contents
The George Bird Grinnell Papers consist of letterpress copybooks, correspondence, subject files, and other papers documenting the life and work of George Bird Grinnell, particularly his pioneering efforts in the American conservation movement. The papers highlight Grinnell's interest in wildlife preservation and the American West and its Indians and his role as a prolific author of books and articles on these subjects. While the papers date from 1859, they contain relatively little material from Grinnell's family, childhood, student days, years teaching at Yale, and first years with Forest and Stream. The bulk of the material represents Grinnell's career from his mid-thirties until the end of his life.
Grinnell left the bulk of these papers to John P. Holman of Fairfield, Connecticut, the president of the Connecticut Audubon Society, who gave them to that society. When John Reiger, who had done extensive research on Grinnell, became president of the Connecticut Audubon Society, he, with the encouragement of the Board of Directors of the Connecticut Audubon Society, arranged for the transfer of these papers to the Yale University Library in 1984. Other material received from Reiger and through purchase was added to the papers in 1988 and 1989.
The George Bird Grinnell Papers are arranged in forty-one boxes. They are organized in two series.
Series I. which is the larger of the two, contains copies of Grinnell's outgoing letters, in the form of letterpress copybooks. These include Grinnell's personal letterpress copybooks from 1886-1929, as well as scattered editorial and business letterbooks for Forest and Stream from 1895-1905. Series II includes incoming letters to Grinnell as well as topical files, photographs, copies of Grinnell's writings, notebooks, clippings, and other papers relating to Grinnell's life.
The letterbooks in Series I include thirty-eight volumes containing copies of Grinnell's outgoing letters. A few of the letters in these letterbooks are handwritten copies of outgoing letters, but the vast majority of the copies were created by wetting the original letter and pressing it against the thin tissue pages. In the process of making such a copy, letters were often blurred, smudged, and crumbled. Poorly made copies are faint and many are illegible. The fragile pages in the volumes have been wrinkled and torn.
The letters in each volume are arranged in chronological order, but an index at the beginning of each volume provides access to these letters by recipient. The personal letterbooks contain letters to numerous individuals and organizations active in conserving natural resources, preserving American wildlife, and protecting the rights and welfare of native Americans. Additional letters concern the history and literature of the American West.
Recipients of Grinnell's letters include government officials, politicians, Indian agents, and colleagues from various organizations in the conservation movement. The letterbooks contain frequent letters to Edward Salisbury Dana, George Gould, Madison Grant, Charles Hallock, Ripley Hitchcock, William Hornaday, Joseph Kipp, Francis E. Leupp, Othniel C. Marsh, Frank and Luther North, Theodore Roosevelt, James W. Schultz, Charles Sheldon, George Shiras, III, Owen Wister, and A. J. Woodcock. Grinnell also wrote to the many Indian leaders and chiefs whom he had met in his western travels including Bear Chief, Bull Calf, and Tall Bull.
Grinnell's letters also record the founding, development, administration, and policy disputes of several organizations associated with the conservation of the American West and its Indian population and with the preservation of game animals and other forms of wildlife. Letters to officers and members of the American Game Protective and Propagation Association, the Indian Rights Association, the National Audubon Society, and the National Parks Association are relevant to those researching the history of these organizations. Letters to officials in the United States Bureau of Indian Affairs and Department of Interior contain discussions of government policy on these issues.
The letterbooks for Forest and Stream are far less inclusive than the volumes of personal letters; they do not cover the entire period of Grinnell's editorship. The volumes labelled editorial (1895-1896, 1901-1902) contain copies of letters relating to the policy, content, and development of the journal, while those labelled as business (1900-1905) contain material relating to the financial operations of the publication.
The papers in Series II are arranged in three sections:Correspondence, Subject files, and Other papers. Correspondence and Subject files both include incoming letters as well as unbound letters written by Grinnell. Grinnell filed many substantive letters in files relating to topics of interest. In total, however, the quantity of incoming letters is minute in proportion to the number of letters in the letterbooks. It is obvious from examining drafts of writings and sheets of notes that Grinnell used some of his incoming letters by drafting on the back sides. That alone, however, does not explain the vast difference in quantity. The files represent only a very selective view of Grinnell's entire career, but they highlight some of his most important contributions.
The Correspondence section begins with several folders of letters arranged in chronological order. These letters are of a fairly general nature and seldom are there more than one or two letters from any particular individual. The correspondence following is more substantive and is arranged according to correspondent's name. The listing for this material also includes cross-references to correspondence from the same individual, which is filed in the subject files.
The listing of correspondence filed by correspondent name includes many names previously cited as recipients of Grinnell's letters. Included are several western men such as T. E. Hofer, J. B. Monroe, the North Brothers, and A. C. Stohr, who wrote to Grinnell concerning his western travels and to keep him abreast of conditions in their states. John R. Eddy, who was in Montana as an agent of the United States Indian Service, wrote many letters concerning the condition of Indians in his area. Other correspondents' letters concern the policies of various conservation organizations or legislation to protect land animals. Among these are John B. Burnham, William T. Hornady, William E. Mershon, Barrington Moore, Charles Sheldon, George Shiras, III, and Robert Sterling Yard.
Files also exist for correspondence received from conservation organizations such as the American Game Protective and Propagation Association, the National Association of Audubon Societies, and the National Parks Association and from publishers of Grinnell's books and book dealers interested in locating books of special interest to Grinnell. These files also include a few early letters by Grinnell to his parents and two letters from William Ludlow inviting Grinnell to join the ill-fated Custer expedition of 1876.
The section Subject files includes letters, printed material, notes, photographs, and drafts and copies of Grinnell's writings arranged by topic. The folder titles are fairly general but often refer to a subject on which Grinnell wrote or an activity in which Grinnell was deeply involved. For example, several folders have titles relating to specific animals, such as "Birds," "Elk," or "Goat." These folders may include writings by Grinnell on the animal as well as background material and notes. Folders such as "Alaska game bill" or "Migratory bird legislation" focus more specifically on efforts to protect wildlife and may contain significant correspondence from individuals and organizations active in promoting protective legislation. Several files concern Grinnell's involvement in preserving national parks.
Files on "West" and "Indians" while quite general in scope contain much correspondence from western acquaintances and from several Indian friends. Grinnell's writings on specific subjects can be found in files such as "Audubon family; Audubon Society," "Bent family; Bent's Old Fort," and "Sheldon, Charles" along with correspondence giving background information on these subjects. Certain files, including "Fraser, George C.," "Marsh expedition," and "Marsh Island," also contain information on Grinnell's travels.
The section Other papers includes material organized by type. The clippings, notes, writings, and photographs included in the section are similar to the materials in Subject files but could not be classified to a single subject. Some of the material such as biographical data, certificates, and clippings about Grinnell is more personal than material in the subject files. Also included in this section is a typescript of a memoir which Grinnell wrote in 1915. The essay covers his life through the year 1883. Other material such as index cards and notebooks concerns many subjects. Drafts of Grinnell's writings, for which there was no other subject file, have been arranged in this section, as have bibliographies for Grinnell's books and articles in Forest and Stream. Similarly, photographs which could not be identified according to subject are included in this section. For both writings and photographs the listing includes references to folders in Subject files which include additional records of this type.
Biographical / Historical
George Bird Grinnell was born in Brooklyn, New York on September 20, 1849. He received his B.A. degree from Yale University in 1870 and did graduate work there under O. C. Marsh, receiving his Ph.D. in 1880. From 1876 until 1911 Grinnell was associated with "Forest and Stream" magazine, becoming editor-in-chief in 1880. Grinnell was active in several organizations instrumental in conserving the American West and protecting wildlife. He was also an authority on the Blackfeet, Cheyenne, and Pawnee Indians, and a prolific writer on Indian folklore and life, as well as on subjects relating to conservation. Grinnell died on April 11, 1938, in New York City.
For more information, consult: Dictionary of American Biography, Vol XXII, Supplement Two., or see additional information available in the repository.
Conditions Governing Access
The entire collection is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 223 instead of the originals.
Forest and Stream; Cheyenne Indians; Conservation of natural resources; Forests and forestry; Frontier and pioneer life -- West (U.S.); Hunting; Indians of North America -- Folklore; Indians of North America; Indians, Treatment of -- North America; Journalism; Pawnee Indians; Pioneers; Alaska; Glacier National Park (Mont.); West (U.S.) -- Description and travel; West (U.S.) -- History -- 1848-1860; West (U.S.) -- History -- 1860-1890; West (U.S.) -- History -- 1890-1945; Yellowstone National Park; Conservationists; Aubrey, Charles; Bannon, Henry Towne, 1867-1950; Barringer, Daniel Moreau, 1860-1929; Bent, George, 1843-1918; Burnham, John B.; Dellenbaugh, Frederick Samuel, 1853-1935; Eddy, John R.; Fisher, A. K. (Albert Kenrick), 1856-1948; Gould, George, 1898-; Grant, Madison, 1865-1937; Grinnell, George Bird, 1849-1938; Grinnell, Joseph, 1877-1939; Hallock, Charles, 1834-1917; Hardy, Manly, 1832-1910; Hershaw, Henry W.; Hodge, Frederick Webb, 1864-1956; Hofer, T. Elwood; Hornaday, William T. (William Temple), 1854-1937; Kipp, Joseph, 1849-1913; Marsh, Othniel Charles, 1831-1899; Merriam, C. Hart (Clinton Hart), 1855-1942; Mershon, Wm. B. (William Butts), 1856-1943; Monroe, J. B.; North, Frank; North, Luther Heddon, 1846-1935; Perrine, James; Phillips, John C. (John Charles), 1876-1938; Riggs, Thomas, 1873-1945; Rowland, Willis; Sanders, James U. (James Upson), 1859-1923; Saunders, Charles Francis, 1859-1941; Schultz, James Willard, 1859-1947; Scott, Hugh Lenox, 1853-1934; Sheldon, Charles, 1867-1928; Shiras, George, 1859-1942; Stohr, A. C.; Woodcock, A.J.; Yard, Robert Sterling, 1861-1945; Audubon family; Grinnell family; United States. Department of the Interior; American Game Protective and Propagation Association; American Museum of Natural History; Boone and Crockett Club; Indian Rights Association; National Audubon Society; National Parks Association (U.S.); Roosevelt Memorial Association
- Letterbooks, 1886-1929; Series I; 9.75 linear feet (24 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains both Grinnell's personal letterbooks and letterbooks concerning Forest and Stream. The personal letterbooks are arranged in chronological order at the beginning of the series. These are followed by the Forest and Stream letterbooks, first two editorial volumes and the two business volumes.
  - Personal, 1886 August 2 - 1888 November 24, 1888 November 27 - 1889 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 1-2, Reel 1U)
  - Personal, 1889 November 26 - 1890 July 23 (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 2U)
  - Personal, 1890 July 29 - 1892 April 6 (Box 2, Folder 4-5, Reel 3U)
  - Personal, 1892 April 7 - 1892 December 23 (Box 2, Folder 6, Reel 4U)
  - Personal, 1894 March 30 - 1896 June 22 (Box 3, Folder 7, Reel 4U)
  - Personal, 1896 June 22 - 1897 July 26 (Box 4, Folder 8, Reel 5U)
  - Personal, 1897 July 26 - 1898 December 19 (Box 4, Folder 9, Reel 5U)
  - Personal, 1898 December 14 - 1900 June 22 (Box 5, Folder 10, Reel 6U)
  - Personal, 1900 June 22 - 1901 December 17 (Box 6, Folder 11, Reel 7U)
  - Personal, 1901 December 17 - 1903 April 22 (Box 7, Folder 12, Reel 8U)
  - Personal, 1903 April 22 - 1904 July 11 (Box 8, Folder 13, Reel 9U)
  - Personal, 1904 July 12 - 1905 December 28 (Box 9, Folder 14, Reel 10U)
  - Personal, 1905 December 29 - 1907 June 19 (Box 10, Folder 15, Reel 11U)
  - Personal, 1907 June 20 - 1909 February 8 (Box 11, Folder 16, Reel 12U)
  - Personal, 1909 February 9 - 1910 March 25 (Box 12, Folder 17, Reel 13U)
  - Personal, 1910 March 25 - 1911 March 23 (Box 13, Folder 18, Reel 14U)
  - Personal, 1911 March 24 - 1912 February 23 (Box 13, Folder 19, Reel 15U)
  - Personal, 1912 February 23 - 1913 April 24 (Box 14, Folder 20, Reel 16U)
  - Personal, 1913 April 25 - 1914 January 22 (Box 14, Folder 21, Reel 17U)
  - Personal, 1914 January 26 - 1914 October 30 (Box 15, Folder 22, Reel 18U)
  - Personal, 1914 October 30 - 1915 June 30 (Box 15, Folder 23, Reel 19U)
  - Personal, 1915 July 1 - 1916 April 15 (Box 16, Folder 24, Reel 20U)
  - Personal, 1916 April 17 - 1917 January 22 (Box 16, Folder 25, Reel 21U)
  - Personal, 1917 January 23-October 25; 1920 December 1-December 22 (Box 17, Folder 26-27, Reel 22U)
  - Personal, 1917 October 31 - 1918 October 7 (Box 18, Folder 28, Reel 23U)
  - Personal, 1918 October 8 - 1919 November 28 (Box 18, Folder 29, Reel 24U)
  - Personal, 1919 November 28 - 1920 December 2 (Box 19, Folder 30, Reel 25U)
    General
    See also: box 17, folder 27
    See also: box 35, folder 194
  - Personal, 1920 December 24 - 1921 December 28 (Box 19, Folder 31, Reel 26U)
  - Personal, 1921 December 28 - 1923 May 24 (Box 20, Folder 32, Reel 27U)
  - Personal, 1923 May 24 - 1925 July 28 (Box 20, Folder 33, Reel 28U)
  - Personal, 1925 July 28 - 1928 October 15 (Box 21, Folder 34, Reel 29U)
  - Personal, 1928 October 23 - 1929 October 17 (Box 22, Folder 35, Reel 30U)
  - Forest and Stream: editorial, 1895 September 20 - 1896 October 8 (Box 23, Folder 36, Reel 31U)
  - Forest and Stream: editorial, 1901 April 26 - 1902 October 8 (Box 23, Folder 37, Reel 32U)
  - Forest and Stream: business, 1900 October - 1902 April (Box 24, Folder 38, Reel 33U)
  - Forest and Stream: business, 1903 December 26 - 1905 January 21 (Box 24, Folder 39, Reel 34U)
- Correspondence, Subject Files, and Other Papers, 1859-1939; Series II; 6.5 linear feet (17 boxes)
  This series is arranged in three sections: Correspondence, Subject files, and Other papers. Each section is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Correspondence
    - General correspondence, 1875-1936 (Box 25, Folder 40-48, Reel 35U)
    - General correspondence and fragments, undated (Box 25, Folder 49, Reel 35U)
    - Albright, Horace M., 1919-1933 (Box 25, Folder 50, Reel 36U)
    - Allen, J. A., 1904-1919 (Box 25, Folder 51, Reel 36U)
    - American Game Protective and Propagation Association, 1913-1922, 1924-1929, undated (Box 25, Folder 52-53, Reel 36U)
    - American Museum of Natural History, 1908-1928 (Box 26, Folder 54, Reel 36U)
      See also: box 25, folder 51
      See also: box 26, folder 63
    - Aubrey, Charles, 1905-1908 (Box 26, Folder 55-56, Reel 36U)
    - Audubon, Harriet B., 1913-1927 (Box 26, Folder 57, Reel 36U)
    - Bannon, Henry, 1923-1925, undated (Box 26, Folder 58, Reel 36U)
    - Barringer, Daniel Moreau, 1911-1925 (Box 26, Folder 59, Reel 36U)
    - Beede, A. Mc G., 1918 (Box 26, Folder 60, Reel 36U)
    - Burnham, John B., 1910-1929, undated (Box 26, Folder 61, Reel 36U)
      See also: box 31, folder 146
      See also: box 33, folders 166-171
    - Chamberlain, Allen, 1916-1924 (Box 26, Folder 62, Reel 36U)
    - Chapman, Frank M., 1919, 1929 (Box 26, Folder 63, Reel 36U)
    - Charles Scribner's Sons, 1905-1925 (Box 26, Folder 64, Reel 36U)
    - Clifford, J. C., 1905-1915 (Box 26, Folder 65, Reel 36U)
    - Condit, L. R. A., 1916-1925 (Box 26, Folder 66, Reel 36U)
    - Deane, Ruthven, 1915-1922 (Box 26, Folder 67, Reel 36U)
    - Dellenbaugh, Frederick S., 1931-1935 (Box 26, Folder 68, Reel 36U)
    - Eaton, Alden, 1930-1935 (Box 26, Folder 69, Reel 36U)
    - Eaton, Howard, 1911-1929 (Box 26, Folder 70, Reel 36U)
    - Eckstorm, Fannie H., 1910-1921 (Box 26, Folder 71, Reel 36U)
    - Eddy, John R., 1907-1914, 1916-1925, undated (Box 27, Folder 72-75, Reel 37U)
    - Ellison, R. S., 1924-1926 (Box 27, Folder 76, Reel 37U)
    - Ely, Alfred
      See: box 29, folder 113
    - Fisher, A. K., 1906-1929, undated (Box 27, Folder 77, Reel 37U)
    - Franklin Bookshop, 1907-1920 (Box 27, Folder 78, Reel 37U)
    - Frederick A. Stokes Company, 1907, 1912, 1918 (Box 27, Folder 79, Reel 37U)
    - Gould, G. H., 1889, 1898-1919 (Box 27, Folder 80, Reel 37U)
    - Grant, Madison, 1898-1931, undated (Box 27, Folder 81, Reel 37U)
      See also: box 30, folders 139-141
      See also: box 32, folder 157
      See also: box 31, folder 144
    - Graves, Henry Solon, 1919-1924 (Box 27, Folder 82, Reel 37U)
      See also: box 36, folder 204
    - Grinnell, Joseph, 1913-1933 (Box 27, Folder 83, Reel 37U)
    - Grinnell family, 1870 (Box 27, Folder 84, Reel 37U)
    - Hallock, Charles, 1876-1910, undated (Box 27, Folder 85, Reel 37U)
    - Hardy, Manly, 1910 (Box 27, Folder 86, Reel 37U)
    - Harper and Brothers, 1910-1923 (Box 27, Folder 87, Reel 37U)
    - Henshaw, Henry W., 1905-1913 (Box 27, Folder 88, Reel 37U)
    - Hodge, F. W., 1911-1929, 1939 (Box 27, Folder 89, Reel 37U)
    - Hofer, T. E. (Billy), 1905-1933, undated (Box 27, Folder 90-92, Reel 37U)
    - Hornady, William T., 1890-1920, undated (Box 27, Folder 93, Reel 37U)
      See also: box 30, folders 139-140
      See also: box 33, folder 164
    - Jeffers, LeRoy, 1919-1926, undated (Box 28, Folder 94, Reel 38U)
    - Lawrence, Robert B., 1919, 1934-1938 (Box 28, Folder 95, Reel 38U)
    - Linderman, F. B., 1914-1916, undated (Box 28, Folder 96, Reel 38U)
    - Ludlow, William, 1875-1876 (Box 28, Folder 97, Reel 38U)
    - Magee, Thomas B., 1915-1923 (Box 28, Folder 98, Reel 38U)
    - Merriam, C. Hart, 1889-1930, undated (Box 28, Folder 99, Reel 38U)
    - Mershon, William B., 1910-1918 (Box 28, Folder 100, Reel 38U)
    - Mershon, William B., 1919-1929 (Box 28, Folder 101, Reel 38U)
      See also: box 29, folder 107
    - Monroe, J. B. (Jack), 1898-1939, undated (Box 28, Folder 102-103, Reel 38U)
    - Moore, Barrington, 1920-1929 (Box 28, Folder 104, Reel 38U)
    - National Association of Audubon Societies, 1904-1935, undated (Box 28, Folder 105-106, Reel 38U)
    - National Parks Association, 1916-1929, undated (Box 29, Folder 107, Reel 39U)
      See also: box 32, folder 153
      See also: box 30, folder 138
    - North brothers, 1910-1924 (Box 29, Folder 108, Reel 39U)
    - Palmer, T. S., 1901-1925 (Box 29, Folder 109, Reel 39U)
    - Perrine, James A., 1905-1920, undated (Box 29, Folder 110, Reel 39U)
    - Phillips, John C., 1921-1929, undated (Box 29, Folder 111, Reel 39U)
    - Pickett, William D., 1911-1912, undated (Box 29, Folder 112, Reel 39U)
    - Records of North American Big Game, 1936-1937 (Box 29, Folder 113, Reel 39U)
    - Reeve, Charles McC., 1902-1934 (Box 29, Folder 114, Reel 39U)
    - Reynolds, C. B., 1911-1929, undated (Box 29, Folder 115, Reel 39U)
    - Riggs, Thomas, Jr.
      See: box 30, folders 139-140
    - Roosevelt Memorial Association, 1923-1931, undated (Box 29, Folder 116, Reel 39U)
    - Rowland, Willis, 1915-1926 (Box 29, Folder 117, Reel 39U)
    - Sanders, James U., 1914-1920 (Box 29, Folder 118, Reel 39U)
    - Saunders, Charles Francis, 1930 (Box 29, Folder 119, Reel 39U)
    - Sawyer, Edward A., 1914-1923, 1929-1930 (Box 29, Folder 120, Reel 39U)
    - Schultz, James Willard, 1905-1930, undated (Box 29, Folder 121, Reel 39U)
    - Scott, H.L, 1909-1929 (Box 29, Folder 122, Reel 39U)
    - Seton, Ernest Thompson, 1933-1935 (Box 29, Folder 123, Reel 39U)
    - Sheldon, Charles
      See: box 27, folder 81
      See: box 31, folder 151
      See: box 32, folder 158
      See: box 35, folder 195
    - Shiras, George, III, 1907-1911, 1920-1935 (Box 29, Folder 124, Reel 39U)
      See also: box 34, folder 179
      See also: box 34, folders 184-186
    - Shoemaker, Henry W., 1925, undated (Box 29, Folder 125, Reel 39U)
    - Smith, DeCost, 1910-1921 (Box 29, Folder 126, Reel 39U)
    - Stohr, A. C. and Fannie, 1911-1925, 1928-1934, undated (Box 29, Folder 127-128, Reel 39U)
    - Stone Witmer, 1913-1929 (Box 29, Folder 129, Reel 39U)
    - Thoburn, Joseph B., 1910-1929 (Box 30, Folder 130, Reel 40U)
    - Tomlinson, O. A.
      See: box 25, folder 50
    - Vaught, L. O., 1912-1926 (Box 30, Folder 131, Reel 40U)
    - Walcott, F. C., 1914-1922 (Box 30, Folder 132, Reel 40U)
    - Wallace, Henry A., 1923-1924 (Box 30, Folder 133, Reel 40U)
    - Wheeler, H. W., 1915-1922, undated (Box 30, Folder 134, Reel 40U)
    - White, John J., 1905-1915, undated (Box 30, Folder 135, Reel 40U)
    - Wissler, Clark
      See: box 26, folder 54
    - Woodcock, Albert J., 1905-1923, undated (Box 30, Folder 136, Reel 40U)
    - Yale University Press, 1919-1929 (Box 30, Folder 137, Reel 40U)
    - Yard, Robert Sterling, 1915-1929, undated (Box 30, Folder 138, Reel 40U)
  - Subject files
    - Alaska game bill, 1917-1920, undated (Box 30, Folder 139-140, Reel 40U)